Guide to the Lee Wilson Dodd Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lee Wilson Dodd papers
1902-1934
YCAL MSS 695
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.51
(7 boxes) + 1 cold storage item
The collection consists of material created by and relating to Lee Wilson Dodd, documenting his career as a playwright and author of fiction. The bulk of the collection consists of drafts and circulating versions of playscripts and other writings by Dodd (including a draft of a single novel, Mouse). Also included are two folders of correspondence, one folder of playbills, and one folder of photographic negatives.
Dodd, Lee Wilson, 1879-1933
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jack Crawford, 1952, and Alan Dodd, 1953.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 8: (Cold storage)(Photographic negatives): Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Lee Wilson Dodd
Lee Wilson Dodd (1879-1933), Yale College 1899, Law School 1902, American playwright and author of fiction.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of material created by and relating to Lee Wilson Dodd, documenting his career as a playwright and author of fiction. The bulk of the collection consists of drafts and circulating versions of playscripts and other writings by Dodd (including a draft of a single novel, Mouse ). Also included are two folders of correspondence, one folder of playbills, and one folder of photographic negatives.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: I. Writings, 1904-1934. II. Other Papers, 1902-1932.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century; Novelists, American -- 20th Century; Dramatists, American -- 20th Century; Negatives (photographic); Playbills; Authors -- United States -- 20th Century; Dramatists -- United States -- 20th Century; Novelists -- United States -- 20th Century; Dodd, Lee Wilson, 1879-1933
- Writings, 1904-1934; Series I; 2.3; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically. Poems, notes, and two untitled play scenarios are filed at the end of the sequence.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of drafts and circulating versions of writings of Lee Wilson Dodd, including plays (full scripts and scenarios), essays and short stories.
  - The Antagonist (playscript), typescript and carbon, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
  - Artie's Mothers (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - At Home (playscript), typescript carbon, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Better Place (short story), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The Boy and the Book (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brown Stone Boyhood (short story), typescript, corrected, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - The Changelings (playscript), typescript carbon, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Enderby's Quest (short story), autograph manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fair Weather Sailors (short story), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Fifty and Twenty-five (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Finishing Fanny (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Great and Little Things (short story), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Haunted (short story), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - The Honorary Member (short story), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Insane Angels (essay), typescript and related correspondence, 1934, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - The Joy Ride
    Related Archival Materials note
    See: The Reckless Age
  - It's a Small World (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Lavengro (playscript), autograph manuscript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 18-19)
  - The Lien of Life (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - The Living Dead (playscript), typescript carbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - The Man Question (playscript), typescript carbon, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Merrymount (opera libretto), typescript, with accompanying correspondence, 1911, 1919 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Modesty (playscript), by Paul Hervieu, translated by Lee Wilson Dodd, typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - The Mortgage Maker
    See: Speed
  - Mother Earth (playscript), typescript, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Mouse (novel), typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Mrs. Beltenham's Archangel (playscript), typescript carbon, undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - The Old Gods (playscript), typescript, corrected, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Pat and Mouse (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Peace and Quiet (playscript), typescript carbon, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Perfect Philistine (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - The Play (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Poet and Cavalier (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - The Reckless Age (playscript), six versions, autograph manuscript and typescript, 1911-1913, undated (Box 3, Folder 34-39)
  - Saving Judy (playscript), two versions, typescript carbon, undated (Box 4, Folder 40-41)
  - Saying and Doing (essay), typescript carbon, circa 1904 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Seeing Red with Ronny (playscript), two versions, typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 43-44)
  - Sheep in Wolves' Clothing (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - The Slender Silence (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Some Thoughts on Democratic Art (essay), autograph manuscript, 1904 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Speed (playscript), typescript and carbon, 1910 (Box 4, Folder 48-49)
  - A Stranger in the House (playscript), four versions, typescript and carbon, 1925, undated (Box 4, Folder 50-53)
  - Strenuous (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - A Strong Man's House (playscript), two versions, typescript carbon, undated (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Things Are Seldom So Nice (short story), typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - The Three Worlds (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - The Tight Rope Lady (playscript), typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Tired (playscript), typescript carbon, undated (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Tullia of Aragon (scenario), typescript carbon, undated (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - The Vision of Tristram Dane (playscript), autograph manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 5, Folder 61-62)
  - The Wander Wraith (poem), typescript carbon, circa 1904 (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Poems, autograph manuscript and typescript, 1914-1933, undated (Box 5, Folder 64-65)
  - Poems, clippings, 1919-1932 (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Notebook, undated (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Notes and fragments of writings, autograph manuscript and typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - "Scenario of a play in four acts," typescript, undated (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - "Scenario of a new play," typescript carbon, undated (Box 6, Folder 70)
- Other Papers, 1902-1932; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  Organized by type of material.
  Series II consists of correspondence, printed ephemera, and photographic negatives.
  - Letters to Jack Crawford, 1902-1905 (Box 7, Folder 71)
  - Correspondence, chiefly relating to Golden Complex and Book of Susan, 1920-1932 (Box 7, Folder 72)
  - Printed ephemera: playbills and one publisher's announcement, 1929, undated (Box 7, Folder 73)
  - Photographic negatives, 1920s (Box 7, Folder 74-75)
    Photographs consist landscapes and portraits of unidentified people, some of which appear to be in Mexico.
- Restricted Fragile Material
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Photographic negatives (Series II) (Box 8 (Cold storage))